We're nearing the end of this super long module where a lot was covered.
Bu sper uzun yryn sonuna yaklayoruz, hepimizin st rtl konumdayz.
Now there's one last feature which I want to show you which you won't use too often but which can
imdi sana sk sk kullanmayacanz, ancak bileenlerinizde yapmak istediiniz baz kk
be extremely valuable for some tiny convenient things you want to do in your components,
kolaylklar iin son derece deerli olabileceini size gstermek istediim son bir zellik var.
mostly when focusing text inputs and stuff like that.
ounlukla metin girdileri ve buna benzer eyler odaklanrken.
Now let me show you what I mean,
imdi ne demek istediimi gstereyim.
we do have a text input in person.js and let's say we want to focus text input of the first person
Hapishane J'de bir metin girii var. S. ve diyelim ki ayrk olarak verildiinde
here whenever it is rendered to the screen.
burada ilk kiinin metin girii zerine odaklanmak istiyoruz.
Now focusing this input is actually not that straightforward here because we would like to call the
zaman noktasnda bu girdi eleman zerinde elde edebileceimiz odak yntemi armak istiyoruz.
focus method we can get on this input element at a certain point of time.
imdi bu girdiyi odaklamak aslnda burada doru deil nk belirli bir
So for example, after componentDidMount or in this method to be precise so that we know that it exists.
Mesela bir bileenin taklmas ya da bu yntemde kesin olmas iin, imdi var
Now
olduunu biliyoruz.
for that, we need access to the input element so that we can call the focus method from this method.
Bunun iin, bu yntemden odaklama yntemini arabilmemiz iin input esine erimemiz gerekiyor.
And there might be some work arounds which you can find with setting some state and then rendering this
Ve baz durumlar belirleyerek ve sonra bu girii koullu olarak odaklanm veya
input conditionally in the focused state or unfocused state
odaklanmam duruma getirerek bulabileceiniz baz alma ortamlar olabilir.
and actually oftentimes you should try to use these work arounds but especially for focusing,
Ve aslnda ou zaman bu evreleri kullanmaya, zellikle odaklanmaya almalsnz.
there's a quick and easy way which is perfectly fine to use, a reference. You can add a special property
referans olarak zel bir zellik veya znitelik ekleyebiliyorsunuz, buna ref gibi isim verilmektedir.
or attributes to input which is called ref, just like key,
Referans kullanmak iin hzl ve kolay bir yol var,
that's a special property known by react. Ref takes a dynamic input which should be a function
Bu re-act ref tarafndan bilinen zel bir zelliktir, dinamik bir girdi alr, bu da bir ilev olmaldr.
so here I'll use an arrow function
Yani burada bir ok fonksiyonu kullanacam.
and in this function, you set up a reference to this element.
Ve bu ileve, bu eye bir referans ayarladnz.
So as I input, you get access to this element, you can name this whatever you want
Dolaysyla girdiim gibi, bu elemente eriebilirsin, ismini istediin gibi verebilirsin.
like inp for input,
Girdi iin P'de olduu gibi.
and in there you can now define a property of this class
Ve imdi orada bu snfn bir zellii tanmlayabilirsiniz.
and this already is important,
Ve bu zaten nemli.
references are only available in stateful components
Kaynaklar yalnzca devlet tm bileenleri iinde mevcuttur.
So in components which are created with class and extends component. There, you can then add a new property
Bylece, snf ile yaratlan ve bileenleri genileten bileenlerde, daha sonra bunu yalnzca ve
to class by simply adding this and then the name of the property, any property you want like input
bunu giren eleman gibi istediiniz herhangi bir mlkn adn ekleyerek bir snfa yeni bir
element,
mlk ekleyebilirsiniz.
again this name is totally up to you.
Yine bu isim tamamen size kalm.
This will create a new property for your entire class,
Bu, tm snfnz iin yeni bir mlk yaratacaktr.
so for the person class which you can therefore use from anywhere in the class and it will be created
Bu nedenle, hangi snfn herhangi bir yerinden kullanabileceiniz kii snf iin ve bir zaman
at a point of time render runs.
noktasnda oluturulacak olan render alr.
So if you later try to access it from within componentDidMount, that will work because componentDidMount
Dolaysyla, daha sonra Mount Dead'in alaca bileenden erimeye alrsanz, rendiiniz ekilde
as you learned is actually executed after render.
monte edilen maliyet bileeni aslnda oluturmadan sonra yrtlr.
Now this alone won't do the trick
imdi bu tek bana hile yapmayacak.
we need to assign a value to this newly created property and the value should be inp,
Bu yeni yaratlan mlke bir deer atamalyz ve deer ENP olmaldr.
so this input element we got access to.
Dolaysyla, eriebildiiniz bu giri esi.
So now we have a property on the class which gives us access to this input element and in componentDidMount
imdi snfta bize bu girdi elemanna eriim imkn tanyan bir mlkmz var
we can now call this.inputElement.focus,
ve bileen miktarnda imdi bu girdi eleman odan arayabiliyoruz.
the focus method is a method available on input elements.
Odaklanma yntemi, giri elerinde kullanlabilen bir yntemdir.
Now if we save this and we open this page, you'll see that the last element is focused,
imdi unu kaydedersek ve bu sayfay aarsak, son enin odaklandn greceksin.
The last one because focus was called for everyone
Sonuncusu nk herkes iin oda aryor.
and therefore since only one element can be focused at a time, it simply sticks to the last one which
Ve bu nedenle, yalnzca bir e ayn anda odaklanabildiinden, yalnzca Focus adl
was rendered, the last one which called focus.
en sonuncusu haline getirilmi olana yapr.
Now if you want to make sure that the first element gets focused, you would need to pass the position
imdi, ilk enin odaklandndan emin olmak istiyorsanz, kalclnza sahip olduunuz konuma
which you have in your persons.js file where you loop with the index,
gemek zorunda kalmazsnz, dizinle nereden dolatnz izleyin.
you would have to pass this as a prop so that you maybe pass position which in the end is just the index
Pasters' pervane olarak kullanmalsnz, bylece belki sonunda sadece dizin olan pozisyona geersiniz ve pozisyon
and if position is 0 then you want to call this.
0 ise o zaman bunu aramak istersiniz.
And then in person.js, you would simply add if statement where you check if this.props.position is equal
Ve daha sonra ahsen, eer bu pervane pozisyonunun sfra eit olup olmadn kontrol ettiiniz if deyimini basite
to zero,
ekleyeceksiniz.
so if this is the first element then you want to call this focus method
Bu yzden ilk e bu ise, bu odak yntemi armak istiyorsunuz.
otherwise, you won't do anything.
Aksi takdirde hibir ey yapmayacaksn.
And now with that, if you click toggle, the first element will be focused.
Ve imdi, gei yaparsanz, ilk e odaklanr.
These are references, important,
Bunlar referans nemli.
you may only use them in stateful components.
Bunlar yalnzca durum bilgisi olan bileenlerde kullanabilirsiniz.
You can also use them on your own components, you're not limited to html elements like input and you should
giri gibi HVM eleri ile snrl olmadnz iin bunlar kullanabilirsiniz ve bunlar zenle kullanmalsnz.
use them with care.
Ayrca kendi bileenlerinizde,
Don't try to get lazy and certainly don't do things like this input element style background color equals
Tembel olmaya almayn ve kesinlikle bu girdi eleman stili arka plan rengi gibi bir
something,
ey yapmayn.
do this with the previous tools you learned for dynamically adjusting styles or for doing anything dynamic.
Dinamik bir ey yapmadan nce stilleri dinamik olarak gvenmek iin reneceiniz nceki aralarla bunu yapn.
This should not be your shortcut for being lazy,
Tembel olduunuz iin ksayolunuz olmamaldr.
it is for a few selected things mostly really about controlling focus or media playback and not for
Birka seili ey iin ounlukla oda veya medya oynatmn kontrol etme hakknda ve stil veya
styling or displaying.
grntleme iin deil.
Use the other tools you learned
renmek iin yukardaki arac kullann.
otherwise you're not doing it
Aksi takdirde yapmyorsun.
the react way.
Yeniden hareket yolu.